<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>S.</title><link>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/</link><atom:link href="https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>S.</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/media/sharing.png</url><title>S.</title><link>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/</link></image><item><title>Gender based violence, education, and technocultures</title><link>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/post/gender-based-violence-education-and-technocultures/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/post/gender-based-violence-education-and-technocultures/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is a translation of an opinion piece published together with my advisor, &lt;a href="https://educacion.uc.cl/cuerpo-academico/planta-ordinaria/errazuriz-valentina/">Valentina Errázuriz Besa&lt;/a>, in the newspaper &lt;a href="https://elpais.com/chile/2024-06-07/violencia-de-genero-educacion-y-tecnoculturas.html">El País&lt;/a>. Saint George School is an elite Catholic school in Santiago, Chile. At the end of May, &lt;a href="https://interferencia.cl/articulos/escandalo-en-el-saint-george-alumnos-de-colegio-elite-crearon-imagenes-de-companeras">news broke&lt;/a> of an incident within the school where male students created AI-generated deepfakes of their female schoolmates to make them appear nude. The images went viral as they were spread both within and outside the school community.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The recent case of students from Saint George School involved in generating and subsequently disseminating AI-modified images to make their classmates appear nude (a phenomenon known as deepfake) has sparked a series of debates. On the one hand, the necessity for legal definitions of acts involving the production of false images and information through technological means has been highlighted, as well as the importance of understanding what happened as an expression of gender-based violence. On the other hand, the role of schools in preventing malicious uses of technology and in digital literacy has been questioned.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We believe that any discussion on how to address the consequences of rapid technological development must be based on the understanding that technology is a sociotechnical product and, therefore, a cultural practice. This means that technologies are not autonomous elements independent of their contexts of production and use, while culture is also permeable to the possibilities offered by technology. In this way, society and technology shape each other and are not separate.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Following this premise, an analysis of what happened with the Saint George students must consider not only the evident sexual aggression and misogyny involved but also the technical elements that made it possible. The images in question were shared in a Telegram group with over 100 participants. The medium through which the event occurred is not irrelevant. &lt;a href="https://journals-sagepub-com.pucdechile.idm.oclc.org/doi/full/10.1177/2056305120984453">Telegram is characterized by offering a sense of anonymity (only a phone number is required to register, and nicknames can be adopted) and facilitating the formation of closed communities that usually can only be accessed by invitation.&lt;/a> These qualities of the platform can favor the normalization of gendered practices, specifically the reaffirmation of masculinity through the exercise of violence against feminized bodies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This does not mean that the application is to blame for generating cultures of sexual aggression. Rather, it indicates that the technological context served, in this case, to proliferate already existing problems. Academic literature has coined the term &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1461444815608807">toxic technocultures&lt;/a> to refer to how the development of software—such as deepfake generators—entails processes of reproducing &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/23268743.2019.1675091">binary gender norms that are overlooked among developer communities&lt;/a>. Particularly, since the content is artificially generated, it becomes easier to dehumanize those involved in the deepfake and to relativize the harm these technologies can cause. Thus, toxic technocultures depend on the combination of a specific cultural configuration and a platform.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Therefore, to devise educational strategies capable of addressing complex phenomena such as the intersection of technologies and oppressive cultures, it is not enough to ban technological artifacts or define exemplary punishments. It is necessary to analyze how the network of relationships involved leads to harmful sexist consequences and what other possible relationships could exist. In this regard, comprehensive sexual education (CSE) can educate towards the healthy consolidation of sexual-affective relationships and the prevention of gender-based violence. Moreover, since technology can be—but is not necessarily—an amplifying agent of sexism and gender-based violence, as well as other forms of injustice (racism, classism, ableism, ageism), it is also necessary to develop educational proposals around digital care. These proposals must consider that technological literacy is not a neutral skill, as it involves situating social practices in digital contexts with a view to constructing spaces based on greater well-being and less harm. Considering these points, it might be possible to dismantle the structures of oppression that permeate both the material and digital worlds.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>On the relationship between cyberfeminisms and datafication</title><link>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/post/on-the-relationship-between-cyberfeminisms-and-datafication/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/post/on-the-relationship-between-cyberfeminisms-and-datafication/</guid><description>&lt;p>The cyberfeminist techno-utopias of the last century dreamed of a cyberspace populated by virtual identities, separate and independent of bodies, and of a non-hierarchical communication of information that would leave behind unidirectional power structures. These imaginaries are countered by the current visualization culture and the algorithmic mediation of content.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/114772.114785">&lt;em>Will the Real Body Please Stand Up?&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, Sandy Stone imagines a state of development of virtual reality in which data can be seen, heard, and even felt. But the truth is that it was not necessary for the technology to achieve reliable three-dimensional forms of representation and science-fiction media for this to make sense. The ways in which data are seen, heard, and felt in the present are, in fact, &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/2053951717700924">mundane&lt;/a>. In my pocket, I always carry an artifact that, by keeping track of my tastes, geolocation, and time management, produces me as a set of data entries with which I can even negotiate, although it often offers me nothing but anxieties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is what José van Dijck has called &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.24908/ss.v12i2.4776">&amp;rsquo;life mining&amp;rsquo; or the datafication of everyday life&lt;/a>. The mining of personal information, its transformation into marketable databases, and the profiling of users based on their online activity make it possible to generate reports on people&amp;rsquo;s actions, habits, and preferences. Together with the operation of algorithms, it is also possible to predict or modify their behavior. Although datafication is not an exclusive phenomenon of the digital era, today it is characterized by the existing technological capacity to automate the collection and analysis of highly personalized data of all kinds at an accelerated pace in order to build big data. Datafication also permeates the field of education, where the practice of permanent data collection and intensive data processing at all levels of educational systems gives rise to the use of big data to examine educational processes over time, as well as to predict outcomes and detect risks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What can cyberfeminisms offer to studies of datafication and, more specifically, datafication of education? First, cyberfeminisms understand data practices as an extension of social life and recognize the potential of technologies in the permanent reconfiguration of various spaces, including education. Second, cyberfeminisms highlight the cybernetic character of current technologies as &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/1357034X95001003003">feedback loops hooked up and responsive to its own environments&lt;/a>. From a cyberfeminist framework, datafication cannot be approached except in relation to the bodies and concrete material situations with which it is entangled. That is, it positions the affective based on the forms taken by the relationships between people, technologies, and educational assemblages, and on what modes of living and feeling are made possible or not in light of this relationships.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cyberfeminism does not have a single definition —hence I opt for the plural &amp;lsquo;cyberfeminisms&amp;rsquo;— but this does not prevent the term from serving to represent what is perhaps most relevant to critical datafication research. As a practice, cyberfeminisms offer tools for political imagination, &lt;a href="https://laboriacuboniks.net/manifesto/xenofeminism-a-politics-for-alienation">advocating for the necessary assembly of techno-political interfaces that are responsive to the risks of technologies that recursively fuse with androcentric cultures&lt;/a> of quantification, anticipation and successism.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>PoliTikTok (Research Project)</title><link>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/research/politiktok/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinic-caneo.netlify.app/research/politiktok/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://politiktok.cl/">Politiktok&lt;/a> is an interdisciplinary research team from the Pontificia Universidad Católica de Chile, funded by the National Agency for Research and Development (ANID) through the Fondecyt Initiation Project No. 11230137. We focus on analyzing how young Chileans use TikTok as a platform to express their opinions on social justice, politics, and current issues. We also focus on the affective economy of affordances and the algorithmic governance of the platform. I am a research assistant on this project.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>